SHADMAN SHAHID

└ <u>+880-1680059310</u> **☑** shadman9085@gmail.com **⋒** <u>Shadman Shahid</u> **♠** <u>shadman-shahid</u>

CAREER SUMMARY

An engineering graduate from Bangladesh University of Engineering and Technology majoring in electronics engineering. 1 year experience of working in a photonics research lab. Interested in the research of photonic technologies for state-of-the-art computational applications. Adept in electromagnetic FDTD technique, nano-electronic device modelling in MATLAB/Python, VLSI design tools, and Deep learning algorithms Enjoys basketball, tutoring and graphic designing in spare time.

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

MIS Department

Advanced Chemical Industries (ACI) Limited

MACHINE LEARNING ENGINEER

Dhaka, Bangladesh July 2021 - Present

- Implemented a sentiment analysis dashboard from newspaper data scraped from webpages of popular Bangla dailies for tracking the company reputation, relevance and presence
- Developed a retail-product embedding model, for more natural and up-to-date prediction of product similarity and recommendation.
- Updated and maintained the Personalized promo and customer lapse dashboard for ACI-logistics.
- Developed a rudimentary chatbot for ACI-Logistics using RASA framework.

Nanophotonics Research Group 🗷

Department of Electrical and Electronic Engineering, Bangladesh University of Engineering and Technology (**BUET**) **RESEARCH ASSISTANT**

Dhaka, Bangladesh March 2021 – Jan 2022

- Primary research focus: Physics driven research of periodic hole array designs for Tamm State based plasmonic lasers
- Authoring funding proposals related to solar photovoltaic (PV) system optimization, floating solar PV systems and flat panel display innovation
- Management of day-to-day activities of the lab and ensuring functionality of devices and hardware.
- Mentoring undergraduate students in their thesis work.

EDUCATION

Bangladesh University of Engineering and Technology

M.Sc in Electrical and Electronic Engineering CGPA - 3.75 on a scale of 4

Ongoing

Bangladesh University of Engineering and Technology

B.Sc in Electrical and Electronic Engineering

Dhaka, Bangladesh Graduated - Feb 2021

Dhaka, Bangladesh

CGPA - 3.86 on a scale of 4 (Top 6%)

Notre Dame College
HIGHER SECONDARY CERTIFICATE: GPA - 5 ON A SCALE OF 5

Dhaka, Bangladesh **Graduated – Aug 2015**

RESEARCH FOCUS

Photonic design optimization, || Photonic integrated circuit, || Machine learning techniques in photonic design, || Photonic inverse design, || Nanophotonics and plasmonics || Computational electromagnetics

RESEARCH PUBLICATIONS

A merged lattice metal nanohole array based dualmode plasmonic laser with an ultra-low threshold

NANOSCALE ADVANCES, ROYAL SOCIETY OF CHEMISTRY (UK)

Dec 2021

- Authors: Shadman Shahid, Shahed-E- Zumrat and Muhammad Anisuzzaman Talukder
- Dual-mode Tamm plasmon resonance observed at the interface between a multi-layer dielectric stack and a metal film is exploited to generate dual-wavelength lasing using a merged lattice nanohole array.

Dual-wavelength hybrid Tamm plasmonic laser 🔀

OPTICS EXPRESS, OPTICA PUBLISHING GROUP

Jun 2022

- Authors: Shahed-E- Zumrat, Shadman Shahid and Muhammad Anisuzzaman Talukder
- Simultaneous excitation of (hybrid) photonic and Tamm plasmonic modes/states come together in a double DBR metal structure for efficient dual-mode lasing.

PROJECTS

Retail product embedding generation

for product recommendation ☑ | Project Documentation (WIP)

Dec 2022 - Ongoing

• Developed an embedding model for a more natural product recommendation and filtering. Used a customized derivative of word2vec called item2vec to train from raw shwapno retail invoice data. (WIP: Work in . progress)

Personalized-Promo Dashboard

Dec 2022 - Ongoing

Dashboard for auto promo generation based on next-month purchase and lapse prediction from retail data.
 Automated periodic (monthly) retail-invoice data extraction with a **Cron**-job script and database procedures. .
 Used **LSTM** and **XGBoost** for prediction.

Sentiment Analysis Dashboard [2] | Project Documentation (WIP)

Nov 2022 - Apr 2023

• A dashboard that analyzes the sentiment of text data scraped from popular Bangla dailies. The dashboard was built using **Python** and **Django**. Scraping was done with **BeautifulSoup** and **Selenium**. Used the . **bertweet-base-sentiment-analysis** and **gensim** package to model topics. (WIP: Work in progress)

Inverse design of thin film stacks through a generative residual global optimization network Res-GLONet 🗗 | Project Report

April 2022

 Faster optimization of a customized thin film dielectric stack for a given response, with the help of a generative neural network coupled to a Transfer Matrix Method (TMM) solver. Idea devised by Jiaqi Jiang and Professor Jonathan Fan

An Investigation into Dual-mode Lasing Response in planar multi-layer Plasmonic laser Systems 🗹

Undergraduate Thesis

Dec 2020

- Two design approaches both already published as mentioned previously have been proposed in order to elicit dual mode lasing response in planar multilayer plasmonic systems for nanophotonic applications.
- Supervised by: Professor Dr. Muhammad Anisuzzaman Talukder

Hamming error correcting code generator and reciever ☑ | Project Report

Dec 2020

• This project shows a prototype of a single forward error correcting system based on least Hamming distance principle. The system was implemented in **verilog** via *Cadence Innovus solution*.

Implementing Tetris Game using Verilog | Project Report

Feb 2019

• A simplified version of the Tetris game was implemented using an FPGA (Field Programmable Gate Array) board - EPF10K70 device - a FLEX 10K device. The EPF10K70 device was programmed using Verilog HDL.

TECHNICAL SKILLS

Programming Languages Python, Verilog, C, C++, MATLAB

Database Management Software Microsoft SQL server

Tools & Softwares MATLAB, Lumerical Suite, Cadence Suite, COMSOL Multiphysics, Microsoft Excel

Deep Learning Tools Pytorch, Tensorflow, Keras, Scikit-learn, Spacy, etc

Web development frameworks Django, Pelican

Editing and Designing Softwares Origin Pro, Adobe Illustrator, Photoshop

Markup Languages ΔT_{EX}

LEADERSHIP AND VOLUNTARY EXPERIENCE

IEEE BUET Student Branch 🗹

CHAIRPERSON - IEEE IAS BUET SB Chapter PROGRAM COORDINATOR

VOLUNTEER

July 2019 - Mar 2021

Sep 2017 – Jul 2019

Jan 2017 – Jul 2017

- Organized events, workshops with different student organizations under IEEE Bangladesh Section.
- Was chief instructor of workshop on Lumerical Inc. (FDTD) for undergraduate students of BUET.

Notre Dame Debating Club

ENGLISH DEBATER

Notre Dame College, Dhaka Sep 2013 - Dec 2015

- Participated and won in numerous debate competitions in school and college level.
- Served as Asst. Gen Secretary of Notre Dame Debating Club for the year 2015.
- · Was the lead designer of publications, posters, logos and merchandise for the club during my tenure

AWARDS AND ACHIEVEMENTS

• Nominated in **University Dean's list** for three out of four levels of undergraduate study.

BUET, Dhaka

• University Merit Scholarship for seven out of eight terms of undergraduate study.

BUET, Dhaka

• 1st prize at Inter University Poster Presentation Contest, at Essonance 2017

IUT, Gazipur, Bangladesh.

REFERENCES

Dr. Muhammad Anisuzzaman Talukder 🗹

PROFESSOR,

Department of Electrical and Electronic Engineering Bangladesh University of Engineering and Technology

Email: anis@eee.buet.ac.bd Contact No: +8801743731065

Dr. Samia Subrina 🗹

PROFESSOR,

Department of Electrical and Electronic Engineering Bangladesh University of Engineering and Technology

Email: samiasubrina@eee.buet.ac.bd Contact No: +8801937959083